Ryszard Mrotek Collection CPAA.86.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Ryszard Mrotek Collection
1955-1984
CPAA.86.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
1.0 box
Attorney Ryszard Mrotek was born in Lwow, which is in today's Ukraine. He spent the WWII in Warsaw, was arrested during the Warsaw Uprising and send to labor camp in Germany. After liberation he attended high school in Germany, worked as interpreter for the United Nations and moved to the US. He became immigration lawyer and settled in Connecticut. He was very active in local political organizations and served as president of the Polish American Congress, Division of Connecticut. He was also active in other organizations and regularly participated in a theatrical productions of a group called Wiatraki Wyobrazni. This collections consist of records of Polish American Congress as well as some personal records.
Mrotek, Ryszard
Biographical/Historical note
Atorney Ryszard S. Mrotek was a distinguished and well-renowned attorney in Hartford and New Britain for 25 years before retiring in 1992. His specialty was Immigration and International Law with a Constitutional expertise. Mr. Mrotek was born in Lwow, Poland, he was a messenger for the Polish Home Army during the 1944 Warsaw Uprising. At age 11, he was taken prisoner by German occupational forces and was later liberated by General Patton's troops. He completed high school in Germany and worked there as an interpreter for the United Nations before emigrating to America. He came to the United States as a refugee, settling in Hartford and becoming a naturalized citizen in 1956. Ryszard received his Bachelor of Arts and Juris Doctorate degrees from the University of Connecticut. He served with the 43rd Infantry Division of the Connecticut National Guard for 18 years, as well as active duty in the U.S. Army from 1956 to 1958. Mr. Mrotek was a prominent leader in the Polish community; he was a President of the Polish American Congress, Division of Connecticut and participated in the production of "Wiatraki Wyobrazni'' (a Polish cultural musical); and, for the rapier wit with which he wrote Polish satire. Mr. Mrotek was also active in the Solidarnosc movement, a successful struggle by the people of Poland for freedom from communist oppression. Recognizing that the struggle for freedom in Poland transcended national boundaries and extended to all people, he never ceased to fight for Human and Civil Rights everywhere. Ryszard will be remembered by his peers and clients for his distinguished legal career. He was a member of the American Immigration Lawyers Association and past Chairperson of the AILA CT Chapter.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of material related to Mr. Mrotek's presidency in the Polish American Congress, Division of Connecticut.
Clippings.; Correspondence.; Immigrants -- Connecticut; Pamphlets.; Poland - Emigration and immigration.; Polish American Congress; Polish American Congress. Connecticut Division; Polish Americans - Connecticut - Biography.
- Ryszard Mrotek - bio and obituary, 1962, 1968, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- R. Mrotek - News clippings related to Mrotek, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- R. Mrotek and Wiatraki Wyobrazni (theater), 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- PAC National - Articles of Incorporation, 1944-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- PAC Conn. District - Arcticles of Incorporation, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- PAC National - By - Laws, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- PAC - correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Cultural Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- PAC National - correspondence, announcements, press releases, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- PAC - 8th National Convention, August 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- PAC District of Connecticut - announcements, press releases, official statements., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Association of Polish Priests in Connecticut - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Government Committee to appoint Polish-American leaders in state administration., 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Articles of Inc. of the Institute for National Development photocopy (Initiative of PAC National office), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- General Sikorski Institute and Museum in London: history and a list of donors., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs of R. Mrotek from event at the Polish National Home in Hartford., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- PAC District of Connecticut - membership campaign., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- PAC Polish-Jewish relations, 1970's (Box 1, Folder 19)
- PAC CT correspondence 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- PAC - declarations, official statements, press releases., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- PAC - correspondence, official statements, press releases., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Exhibition of Polish Culture, Science, Art, in New Britain, May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- PAC Copernicus Celebrations- 500th Anniversary of birth., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- PAC National - correspondence, announcements., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- PAC reaction to the Gdansk shipyard incidents in December of 1970 and aftermath - press releases/clippings (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Polish American issues - clippings, articles., 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Dr. Michael Peszke and the Cultural Committee. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- PAC State Divisions, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Polish-Hungarian World Federation - correspondence, announcements, press releases., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Polish Studies at Central Connecticut State College - press releases, clippings., 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- 50th Anniversary of the Battle of Warsaw., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Pulaski Day Parade., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Jakoboski, Theodore P. - Correspondence., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- PAC District of Connecticut - Endorsement of Julius J. Kremski for State Comptroller., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Poland - Immigration Law, official publications, clippings., 1960's (Box 1, Folder 36)
- The Polish University Club of Connecticut., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- PAC National vs ABC TV for Equal Time; Discrimination and Polish Jokes., 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Ryszard Mrotek - interview for local TV Program, notes, publicity for PAC., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Ethnic Issues - clippings, congressional records., 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Amnesty International - pamphlet and clippings related to situation in Poland., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- PAC-Anti-Defamation and anti-discrimination., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Stanley Pac - Berkowitz article controversy., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- PAC Washington Office - report., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- The Ethnic American, an essay by Senator Barbara Mikulski reprint from "The Polish Women's Voice". (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Ryszard S. Mrotek 1976 campaign for Congress. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Pulaski Day Parade, 1967, 1968, 1970, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- "Project Pole," 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Various anniversary booklets and publications., 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Miscellaneous., 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- R. Mrotek - Misc. correspondence., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 51)